Guide to the Tjeerd H. van Andel Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Tjeerd H. van Andel papers
1950-2006
SC0349
Van Andel, Tjeerd H. (Tjeerd Hendrik), 1923-.
21.5 Linear feet (20 boxes)
The collection includes correspondence, research, publication and committee files, with some photographs.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers were given to Stanford University by Tjeerd H. van Andel in 1988 and 2009.
Information about Access
The collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Born in the Netherlands, Tjeerd H. van Andel came to the United States in 1957. He taught at Scripps Institute of Oceanography and Oregon State before coming to Stanford in 1976. He was an authority on the geology of ocean floors and mid-ocean ridges, with an interest in the prehistory of landscape and civilization which has led to work on climatic change and its economic ramifications. He was a co-leader of Project FAMOUS (French American Mid-Ocean Undersea Study), data from which led directly to the confirmation of plate tectonic theory. Van Andel died in 2010.
Description of the Collection
The collection includes correspondence, research, publication and committee files, with some photographs.
Access Terms
FAMOUS (French American Mid-Ocean Undersea Study).; Stanford University. Department of Geology. Faculty.; Van Andel, Tjeerd H. (Tjeerd Hendrik), 1923-.; Archaeology; Galapagos Rift; Geology.; Mid-Atlantic Ridge; Oceanography; Plate tectonics; Sea floor spreading
Collection Contents
- Papers, Series 1
  - Research Files, 1950-1983; Subseries 1
    - Rhine sediments, Venezuela, Gulf of Mexico, Colorado River (Box 1)
    - Photographs, negatives -- Gulf of Calif. (Box 1)
    - Recife, Paria, Mediterranean cruise, Orinoco Delta, Timor Sea, ca. 1956-68 (Box 1)
    - Mid-Atlantic Ridge, 1967-69 (Box 2)
    - Washington, 1965 (Box 2)
    - South Atlantic, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Circe 8 -- Angola, 1972; Walvis shelf, 1971 (Box 2)
    - Circe 9 -- South Atlantic, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Venezuelan Cretaceous, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Ascensien Island, 1971 (fracture zone) (Box 3)
    - Diatreme field trip, N. E. Arizona, 1970 (Box 3)
    - LEG XVI, 1971 (inc. photos) (deep sea drilling project) (Box 3)
    - Panama basin, Southlow expedition, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Project FAMOUS (French American Mid-Ocean Undersea Study), 1975 (Box 3)
    - Project FAMOUS, 1975-76 (Box 4)
    - AMAR, 1978 (Box 5)
    - Cayman trough; ALVIN cruise, 1978 (Box 5)
    - Galapagos, 1975-79; ALVIN, ANGUS (Box 5)
    - Mid-Ocean Ridge ms, 1979-81 (Box 5)
    - Galapagos, 1979 (Box 6)
    - Equatorial Pacific, 1976 (Box 6)
    - Paleoceanography, undated (Box 6)
    - South Atlantic, 1977 (Box 6)
    - Biostrat -- Worsley, 1975 (Box 6)
    - Indian Ocean (Box 6)
  - Archeology, 1979-1984; Subseries 2
    - Stanford Archeology Program (Box 6)
    - Arch/Geo Chair, 1986-87 (Box 6)
    - Archeology England Trip, 1980 (Box 6)
    - Geo-archeology, Shackleton papers (Box 7)
    - Peru; proposal/plan, 1986 (Box 7)
    - Stanford on the Aegean, funding (Box 7)
    - Argolid survey, 1980-84 (Box 7)
    - Halos/Reinders (Box 7)
    - Torres Straits project (Box 7)
    - Offshore, 1982 (Box 7)
    - Greece field, 1983-86 (Box 7)
  - Publications, Subseries 3
    - GSA/Geology magazine (Box 7)
    - Journal Marine Research (Box 7)
    - Comments on Earth Sciences (Box 7)
    - Jour. Geophysics Research (Box 7)
    - Revue Geol. Dyn. (Box 7)
    - Deepsea Research (Box 7)
    - Shelf Sediment book, 1963 (Box 7)
    - Seawater Text (Box 7)
    - Woollard Symposium, 1984 (Box 7)
    - Indian Ocean -- photographs, negatives (Box 8)
    - Portable Stanford, 1980 (Box 8)
    - Earth History, 1986 (Box 8)
    - Lecture notes, public, 1984 (Box 8)
    - Book reviews, misc (Box 8)
  - Scripps Institute of Oceanography and Oregon State University, Subseries 4
    - Personal, SI0 (Box 8)
    - SI0, students (Box 8)
    - Personal, OSU, 1968-76 (Box 8)
    - Industrial Assoc. Program (Box 8)
    - OSU - students (Box 8)
    - 1974 sabbatical (Box 8)
  - Stanford Committees, Alumni Association, Clipbook, 1976-1988; Subseries 5
    - Stanford Senate, 1977-79 (Box 8)
    - Steering Committee (Box 8)
    - S-CEIT, 1978-79 (Box 8)
    - Overseas Committee. APC/SOS, 1983 (Box 9)
    - CUAFA -- chairmanship, 1980-84 (Box 9)
    - Centennial Comm., 1985-87 (Box 9)
    - Stanford Senate, 1985-87 (Box 9)
    - Earth Sciences Council (Box 9)
    - School of Earth Sciences - memos (Box 9)
    - Freshman Advisees (Box 9)
    - Stanford Alumni Association, 1984-85 (Box 9)
    - California Academy of Sciences (Box 9)
    - Geophysics Department (Box 10)
    - Earth History (Box 10)
    - HuBio -- Climate course (Box 10)
    - News clippings (Box 10)
    - Stanford students (Box 10)
  - Grants, Societies, Committees, International Service, Subseries 6
    - API -- grants-in-aid, 1962 (Box 10)
    - NSF -- Grant proposals, 1960-62 (Box 10)
    - NSF -- Atlantic grant, 1965-71 (Box 10)
    - NSF -- East Pacific depositional, 1971 (Box 10)
    - NSF -- 1974-81 (Box 10)
    - NSF -- Paleoceanography, 1976-79 (Box 11)
    - ONR -- before 1967, 1968-81 (Box 11)
    - ACS/PRF proposals (Box 11)
    - Cal Research grant, 1962 (Box 11)
    - F. J. Pettijohn symposium (Box 11)
    - Consulting -- Northrop Ocean Syst. (Box 11)
    - Univ. of Colorado -- summer school 1961-62 (Box 11)
    - UC Berkeley; 1963, 1967 (Box 11)
    - Woods Hole summer (Box 11)
    - AAPG: Marine Geology, Continuing Education Program (Box 11)
    - American Association of Petroleum Geologists (Box 11)
    - AGI - Tours (Box 11)
    - GSA, 1970-76 (Box 11)
    - OSI, Board of Directors (Box 11)
    - Australia (Box 11)
    - Marine Council (Box 11)
    - US Geodynamics Comm. -- Rio de Janeiro (Box 11)
    - Nasca plate program group (Box 11)
    - NAS Ocean Science Comm. (Box 11)
    - NSF general (Box 11)
    - IDOE, 1976-77 (Box 12)
    - NASCO (Box 12)
    - National Academy of Science -- Freedom of the Sea panel, 1973 (Box 12)
    - Continental margin, 1976-77 (Box 12)
    - NAS/Geophysical Studies, 1978-79 (Box 12)
    - Stanford Chautauqua, 1976-77 (AAAS) (Box 12)
    - Ocean lab plans (Box 12)
    - NATO (Box 13)
    - CLIMAP, 1973 (Box 13)
    - Naval research workshop (Box 13)
    - JOA Paleoc. (Box 13)
    - Comm Marine Geology (Box 13)
    - NRC/Glomar Explorer (Box 13)
    - Margin drilling, 1980 (Box 13)
    - UNOLS (Box 13)
    - SCOR, 1971-78 (Box 13)
    - IOC/Atlas committee (Box 13)
    - Brown University (Box 13)
    - Navy Multibeam (Box 13)
    - LSU Geology Review, 1976 (Box 13)
    - JOIDES/DSDP (Box 14)
    - Consulting, lectures, conferences (Box 14)
    - Miscellany (Box 14)
    - Miscellany (Box 15)
  - Correspondence, 1963-1986; Subseries 7
    - Correspondence, 1963-1986, A-J (Box 16)
    - Correspondence, 1963-1986, K-Z (Box 16)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-2009-221
  - Deep Sea Cruises - Data, Subseries 1
    - Galapagos -- Angus 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Galapagos -- Angus 9 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Galapagos -- Angus 10 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Galapagos -- Angus 15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Famous -- Alvin -- 521 -- West Margin (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Famous -- Alvin -- 526 -- East Margin (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Famous -- Alvin -- 527 -- East Margin (South) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Famous -- Alvin -- 527 -- Mid Atlantic Ridge 37 degrees N (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Famous Misc (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Famous Photos -- Libec -- Alvin (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Teaching Materials, Subseries 2
    - Artwork for New Views (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
    - Artwork for Cambridge Lecture Courses (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
    - Slides for First Year Geology Lectures (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Lecture Notes -- Cambridge (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - A (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, Subseries 3
    - Ba-Bi (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Bj-Bz (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - C (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - D (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - E-F (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Frankel (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - G (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Ole Grön (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - H (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Sarah Hoffman (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - I-J (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - K (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - L (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - M (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - N-O (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - P (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Q-R (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Curtis Runnells (Box 2, Folder 11-13)
    - S-Sha (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - She-Sz (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
    - T (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - V (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - W-Z (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Zangger (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Stage 3 Project, Subseries 4
    - Stage 3 -- Final Product (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Stage 3 -- Project Grants (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Instructions, Data, & Processing (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - GISP2 Stress Curve (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Trees or no trees (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Other Research Projects, Subseries 5
    - South African Coastlines (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Mediterranean Coastal Migration (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Kostenki -- Tephra Project (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Small NW Asia Black Sea Projects (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Proposal for Ukraine (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Book Chapter for 18K (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Coastal Italy (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Ownership of Time (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Work with Bernie Weninger -- Radiocarbon Calibration (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - C.V. and Bibliography (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Goodwin Institute Development -- 96 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Goodwin Institute Camqua/Journal (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Sub-Department Quaternary Science Dissolution (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Library 2001 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Library 2002 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Battle Between the University Library and Smaller Departments (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Library from June 2006 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Library (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Quaternary MPhil (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Graduate Students: Lucia de Abreu (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Graduate Students: Andy Wheeler (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Graduate Students: William Davies (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Graduate Students: Suzie England (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Miscellaneous Personal Items (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Fellow of Clare Hall (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Archaeological Association -- Boston University (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - California Academy of Sciences -- Royal Netherlands Academy of Science (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Rip-Rapp Award (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - TVA Early Research, Subseries 6
    - TVA's Masters Research (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - TVA's Early Nature Studies (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Climap -- Imbric -- Wally Broeker (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Palaeo-Oceanography (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Stanford Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Stanford Students: Naomi Oreskes (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Public Service: Monterey Institute (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Publishers (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Television and Radio Collaborations (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Editorials to Geology Journal (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Translations of TVA books (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Conferences and Projects, Subseries 7
    - Japanese Attitudes to the Sea (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - A Conference on Climate Change (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Mesolithic Coastlines (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Science Based Archaeology -- Neanderthals (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Venice (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Holocene Africa (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - McDonald Lecture (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Efched (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Greek Research, Subseries 8
    - Origins of Agriculture: Journal of Mediterranean Architecture (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Southern Argolid Coastal Study (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Book Reviews of Southern Argolid (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - End of the Southern Argolid (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Neolithic Conflict in Greece (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Greek Soil Erosion (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Review of Bittlestone's Odysseos (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Proposal for Writing of Francthi (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Palaeolithic Polje (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Moephi Ash -- NW Greece (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Neolithic Thessaly -- Magoula Study (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Gulf of Evvia (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Greek Marine Geophysics (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Coastal Mesolithic of Greece (Box 4, Folder 31)